A Guide to the Paul Ehrlich papers FA135
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Laboratory Notebooks, 1883-1912; 15 letters
  - undated (Berlin period about 1895?), small brown leather notebook, with golden decoration, no date but has notations in Ehrlich's hand about various concentrations of toxins; 8.7 × 14.3 × 0.9 cm. (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - 1895-1896 (Berlin period?), medium sized brown diary in Ehrlich's hand; 14.0 × 17.5 × 2.0 cm. (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - 1896, medium sized black leather diary with gold border / Ehrlich / loose notes; 10.7 × 17.0 × 1.5 cm. (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - 1897?, thin black notebook (medium size) in Ehrlich's hand / includes blue blotting paper; 16.7 × 20.8 × 0.5 cm. (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - 1887 December 22-1889 February 17, thick hardcover book, labeled "Buch XXVII, December 22, 1887-February 17, 1889", some notations by Ehrlich; 17.4 × 21.1 × 3.0 cm. (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - 1898 February 15-June 1, thick hardcover book, labeled "Buch XXVIII, February 15, 1898-June 1, 1898", some notations in Ehrlich's hand; 17.5 × 21.1 × 1.8 cm. (Box 38, Folder 10)
  - 1898 July 2-21, black leather, "Buch XXX" / some notations in Ehrlich's hand; 17.0 × 20.7 × 0.5 cm. (Box 38, Folder 11)
  - 1898 July 23-September 24, black leather, "Buch XXXI", some notations in Ehrlich's hand; 16.8 × 20.7 × 0.5 cm. (Box 38, Folder 12)
  - 1898 September 29-December 8, black leather, "Buch XXXII" / some notations in Ehrlich's hand; 16.8 × 20.9 × 0.5 cm. (Box 38, Folder 13)
  - 1898, thick brown hardcover book, all in Ehrlich's handwriting / Loose notes inside; 18.2 × 21.2 × 2.3 cm. (Box 38, Folder 14)
  - 1912, very small notebook, all in Ehrlich's handwriting / loose printed cards inside (Box 38, Folder 14)
- Blöcke (Laboratory Notes and Instructions), about 300 cards (Box 39-40)
  Cardboard cards (5x8), many colors, with daily instructions to laboratory coworkers.
- Memorabilia
  - 7 very long penholders; 1 short penholder; 3 letter openers (Box 41)
  - 2 rulers; 11 colored pencils; 1 flat pencil holder; 1 small vial (Box 41)
  - 3 cigar knives; 1 sham cigarette in small case; 2 wooden stethoscopes (Box 41)
  - 1 reflex hammer; 1 metal protractor (Box 41)
  - 2 silver pieces in case with the inscription "Den 23. März 1867" (Box 41)
    1) insignia stamp.
    2) penholder (present for Ehrlich's confirmation).
  - 3 silver pieces in case with the inscription: "Den 4. März 1855" (Box 41)
    1) spoon with P.E. inscribed.
    2) knife with P.E. inscribed.
    3) fork with P.E. inscribed (present for Ehrlich's first birthday, though the date on the case does not correspond to his birthday on March 14).
  - 1 black leather case with Ehrlich's calling cards, 6 cards (Box 41)
  - 1 silk ribbon with silver fringes from Paul Ehrlich's grave (Box 41)
  - Hill's Vest-Pocket German-English Dictionary, David (Box 41)
  - McKay Publisher, Philadelphia, 1898 (Box 41)
- Commemorative Plaques
  - 7 plaques given to Paul Ehrlich (Box 42)
    - Liebig-Gedenk Münze, gold, framed, given to Ehrlich by the German Chemical Society, 1
    - A.V. Cornil, no date, in blue case, undated; 2
    - Carl Weigert, no date, in red case, undated; 3
    - No name, 1883, 4
    - William H. Welch - from his friends, 5
    - Herman von Helmholz, 1894; 6
    - Carlo Forlanini, University of Milano, 1932, in red case, 7
  - 1 pin: Emil von Behring and Paul Ehrlich, 1854-1954 (Box 42)
  - 2 stamps of Paul Ehrlich, framed in glass (Box 42)
- Photographs
  There are 57 photographs of Paul Ehrlich, they are in Box No. 43; Folder No. 1; and on shelf. There are 3 negatives, 2 are glass, one is on film. One of the glass slides is in color the other is black and white.
  - Ehrlich's birth-house, 3 photographs (Box 43)
  - Strehlen, 1 photograph (Box 43)
  - Ehrlich's grave, 3 photographs (Box 43)
  - Ehrlich's grandfather, 2 photographs (Box 43)
  - Ehrlich's grandfather (drawing), 1 photograph (Box 43)
  - Ehrlich's grandmother (drawing), 1 photograph (Box 43)
  - Ehrlich's parents, 1 photograph (Box 43)
  - Ehrlich's mother, 1 photograph (Box 43)
  - Ehrlich's father, 1 photograph (Box 43)
  - Ehrlich's parents house interior in Berlin, 4 photographs (Box 43)
  - House on Paul Ehrlich street, 1 photograph (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Ehrlich and members of the laboratory, 1 photographs (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Ehrlich's deathbed, 2 photographs (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Ehrlich's grandmother, 1 photographs (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Ehrlich's grandfather, 1 photographs (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Ehrlich's mother alone, 1 photographs (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Ehrlich's mother with her children, 2 photographs (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Ehrlich's with his sisters, 1 photographs (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Joseph Pinkus, 1 photographs (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Pinkus house interior, 8 photographs (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Pinkus Factory, 1 photographs (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Hedwig Ehrlich, nee Pinkus, 18 photographs (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Ehrlich daughters (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Stefanie and Marianne, 16 photographs (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Ehrlich grandchildren (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Schwerin: Hans-Wolfgang and Günther, 12 photographs (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Dr. and Mrs. Ernst Schwerin & factory, 1 photographs (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Schwerin dog Lilo, 1 photographs (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Landau: Dolly, Susanne and Matthias, 6 photographs (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Landau house in Göttingen, 10 photographs (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Dr. K. Shiga, Japan, 1939; 2 photographs (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Dinner at the Waldorf-Astoria when Hedwig Ehrlich arrived in the U.S.A. in 1941 (Box 44, Folder 2)
- Guestbooks
  - "Fremdenbuch" 1 book started August 24, 1903 and ends September 14,?? (most likely from the laboratory), 1903 August 24-?? September 14 (Box 45)
  - "Gästebuch" 2 books: 1) starts July 20, 1901 ends? 1914, 1901-1914 (Box 45)
  - "Gästebuch" 2 books: 2) starts October 22, 1914 ends November 30, 1937, 1914 October 22-1937 November 30 (Box 45)
- Newspaper clippings, magazines and miscellaneous printed matter
  - Newspaper clippings about Paul Ehrlich before 1915 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Magazines: Simplicissimus - 1910, Jugend (2) -1910, Russian-1914 Der Weltspiegel, 1914, Deutsche Medicinische Wochenschrift - 1914, Ost und West - 1916 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - McClures Magazine, 2 items (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Cartoons about 606, 10 items (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Articles about Salvarsan, 1911 1914; 2 items (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Detective stories, 1909 April 1909 November; 2 items (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - Russian film strips of Paul Ehrlich (23), booklet by Gonder, dinner menu 1910, invitation to a celebration at the University of Berlin, 1888, invitation to a celebration in Sweden, 1908 (not connected with the Nobel Prize), program of celebration of the 50th anniversary of the Berlin Medical Society, 1910, birth announcement, 1911 (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Various mementos from dinners at: Nobel celebration, at court of Kaiser Wilhelm II (including menus), and at a Women's Association (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings and articles written after 1915 (20), 20 items (Box 46, Folder 9)
    Including a reprint from Herman Pinkus.
- Paul Ehrlich - Reprints, 1885-1914
  - "Das Sauerstoff Bedürfhis des Organismus", Hirschwald Verlag, Berlin, pp. 1-167, 2 copies, 1 with inscription to Hedwig Ehrlich, 1885 (Box 47)
  - "Über die Methylenblaureaction der lebenden Nervensubstanz", reprint from Deutsche Medizinische Wochenschrift, Berlin, pp 1-12, with inscription to Hedwig, 1886 (Box 47)
  - "Die Wertbemessung des Diphtherieheilserums und deren theoretischen Grundlagen", Klinisches Jahrbuch, Fischer Verlag, Berlin, pp 1-34, with inscription to Hedwig, 1897 (Box 47)
  - "Experimental Researches on Specific Therapeutics", The Harben Lecture of 1907, H.K. Lewis, London, 1908 pp 1-95, small book with inscription to Hedwig (Box 47)
  - "Chemotherapeutische Trypanosomen-Studien", Berliner Klinische Wochenschrift, No. 9, pp 1-42, with inscription to Hedwig, 1907 (Box 47)
  - "Über den jetzigen Stand der Chemotherapie", Berichte der deutschen chemischen Gesellschaft, Berlin, 2 copies, 1 with inscription to Hedwig, 1909 (Box 47)
  - "Chemotherapie von Infektionskrankheiten", Zeitschrift fur ärztliche Fortbildung, Fischer Verlag, Jena, No. 23, pp 1-12, 1909 (Box 47)
  - "Über Partialfunktionen der Zelle", Nobel lecture, delivered in Stockholm December 11, 1908, Royal Printers, Stockholm, pp 1-19, 1909 (Box 47)
  - "Aus chemotherapeutischem Gebiet", Deutsche Revue, Stuttgart, pp 1-15, 1911 (Box 47)
  - "Grundlagen und Erfolge der Chemotherapie", Enke Verlag, Stuttgart, pp 1-26, 1911 (Box 47)
  - "Aus der Theorie und Praxis der Chemotherapie", Klinkhardt Verlag, Leipzig, pp 1-28, 2 copies, 1 with inscription to Hedwig, 1911 (Box 47)
  - "Chemotherapie", lecture given in the presence of Wilhelm II on October 24, 1911 in Berlin, oversized reprints, 1912
  - "Zum Salvarsanpreis", Deutsch Medizinische Wochenschrift, No. 26, pp 1-4, 1914 (Box 47)
- Bibliography by Hans Sachs, prepared at the occasion of Paul Ehrlich's 60th birthday, reprint from the Festschrift, Fischer Verlag, Jena, 1914 (Box 47)
- Chicago visit, 1904 (Package 1)
  Paper clippings of visit and receipt of honorary doctorate in Chicago, 1904, in black album.
- Vellum case (Package 2)
  Large folder given to Paul Ehrlich at his 60th birthday by friends and colleagues, originally containing articles and speeches, now empty.
- 70th birthday celebration, 1924 (Package 2)
  Booklet of program of the 70th birthday celebration in Tokyo 1924, in Japanese, with signatures of the participants.
- Chemotherapy chart (Package 3)
  Very large chart: "Entwicklung der Chemotherapie", describing in 19 points the development of chemotherapy, covering the years 1891 to 1922, author unknown.
- Weigert family tree (Package 3)
  Large handpainted family tree of the Weigerts, Paul Ehrlich's mother's family.
- Obituary albums (Package 4)
  3 oversized albums: "Paul Ehrlich + 20. August 1915", filled with paper clippings from all over the world and special reprints from various scientific publications (1 album has Martha Marquardt's name inside); many clippings are in duplicate.
  1 black file folder: "Dokumenten Mappe", containing condolence telegrams and letters from officials and friends, including a telegram from Wilhelm II (30 telegrams, 30 letters, 5 cards).
- Paul Ehrlich's death mask (Package 5)
  Plaster impression, in case.
- Diplomas of Orders and Societies, Maps stored in map folders or packages.
  - Die Senckenbergische Naturforschende Gesellschaft, Corresponding Member, 1887 April 27; 1 (Folder 1)
  - Die Senckenbergische Naturforschende Gesellschaft, Ordinary Member, 1899 December 6; 2 (Folder 2)
  - Medical Society of Sweden, 1900 March; 3 (Folder 3)
  - Royal Society of Sciences, Copenhagen, Foreign Member, 1900 April 6; 4 (Folder 3)
  - Society of Biology, France, Corresponding Member, 1900 December 15; 5 (Folder 4)
  - The Society of Internal Medicine in Berlin, Honorary Member, 1902 March 16; 6 (Folder 5)
  - International Society against Tuberculosis, Berlin, Honorary Member, 1902; 7 (Folder 5)
  - The Royal Academy of Medicine, Turin, Corresponding Member, 1903 May 29; 8 (Folder 6)
  - The Silesian Society for Home Culture, Corresponding Member, 1903 December 17; 9 (Folder 7)
  - The Society of Internal Medicine, Vienna, Honorary Member, 1903 December 17; 10 (Folder 7)
  - Academy of Sciences, Bologna, Corresponding Member, 1904 January 17; 11 (Folder 8)
  - Kharkov Society of Physicians, Honorary Member, 1904 February 20; 12 (Folder 9)
  - The Royal Imperial Society of Physicians, Vienna, Honorary Member, 1904 March 18; 13 (Folder 10)
  - University of Chicago, Honorary Doctorate, 1904 March 21; 14 (Folder 11)
  - The New York Academy of Medicine, Honorary Fellow, 1904 April 2; 15 (Folder 12)
  - Letter and diploma from Universal Exposition, St. Louis, Grand Prize, 1904; 16 (Folder 12)
  - The German Medical Society of New York, banquet in honor of Paul Ehrlich, 1904 April 18; 17 (Folder 13)
  - National Academy of Sciences, Washington, Foreign Associate, 1904 April 21; 18 (Folder 14)
  - The Medical Society of Moscow, Honorary Member, 1904 April 21; 19 (Folder 15)
  - Royal Society of Sciences, Göttingen, Foreign Member, 1904 October 14; 20 (Folder 16)
  - Royal Society of Medical and Natural Sciences, Brussels, Corresponding Member, 1904 December 5; 21 (Folder 17)
  - The Royal Society of Edinburgh, Honorary Fellow, 1904 December 28; 22 (Folder 17)
  - Royal Medical Society, Budapest, Honorary Member, 1905 December 9; 23 (Folder 18)
  - University of Aberdeen, document in Latin, 1906; 24 (Folder 19)
  - Medical Society of Finland, Honorary Member, 1906 February 10; 25 (Folder 19)
  - The Society of Physicians, Munich, Honorary Member, 1906 October 10; 26 (Folder 20)
  - Society of Biology, France, Associate Member, 1906 December 22; 27 (Folder 20)
  - Royal Academy dei Lincei, Rome, Foreign Member, 1907 September 30; 28 (Folder 21)
  - The Medical Society of Berlin, Honorary Member, 1907 December 18; 29 (Folder 21)
  - The Society of Exotic Pathology, (Pasteur Inst.) Honorary Member, 1908 February 12; 30 (Folder 22)
  - The Swedish Medical Society, Stockholm, Honorary Member, 1908 April 21; 31 (Folder 22)
  - The Physical-Medical Society of Erlangen, Honorary Member, 1908 June 27; 32 (Folder 23)
  - The Society of Natural Sciences and Medicine of Dresden, Honorary Member, 1908 November 14; 33 (Folder 23)
  - Society of Microbiology in St. Petersburg, Honorary Member, 1909 January 16; 34 (Folder 24)
  - The Medical Society, St. Petersburg, Honorary Member, 1909 February 24; 35 (Folder 25)
  - The Royal Academy of Turin, Honorary Member, 1910 May 15; 36 (Folder 26)
  - The Royal Academy of Medicine, Turin, Honorary Member, 1910 May 20; 37 (Folder 27)
  - The Royal Society of London, Foreign Member, 1910 June 30; 38 (Folder 28)
  - Serbian Medical Society, Honorary Member, 1910 September 14; 39 (Folder 29)
  - Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences, Foreign Member, 1910 October 26; 40 (Folder 29)
  - Society of Silesians in Berlin, Honorary Member, 1910 October 29; 41 (Folder 30)
  - Society of Pediatricians, St. Petersburg, Honorary Member, 1910 December 15; 42 (Folder 30)
  - The Dermatological Society of Vienna, Honorary Member, 1910 December 28; 43 (Folder 30)
  - Imperial Institute of Experimental Medicine, St. Petersburg, Honorary Member, 1911; 44 (Folder 31)
  - International Exposition on Hygiene, Dresden, Honorary Diploma, 1911; 45 (Folder 32)
  - Imperial Caucasian Society of Medicine, Tiflis, Honorary Member, 1911 January 9; 46 (Folder 33)
  - Imperial Society of Medicine, Constantinople, Honorary Member, 1911 February 17; 47 (Folder 34)
  - Royal Society of Sciences, Upsalla, Ordinary Member, 1911 April 7; 48 (Folder 35)
  - University of Breslau, Honorary Doctorate, with 3 copies in leather covered cylindrical holder, 1911 August 3 (Package 7)
  - Royal Academy of Medicine of Belgium, Honorary Foreign Member, 1911 December 30; 49 (Folder 36)
  - International Exposition on Social Hygiene, Rome, 1911-1912; 50 (Folder 36)
  - Royal Medical Society of Edinburgh, Honorary Member, 1912; 51 (Folder 37)
  - National University of Athens, Honorary Doctorate, 1912 March 8; 52 (Folder 38)
  - Society of the Veterinary Institute, Kharkov, Honorary Member, 1912 March 16; 53 (Folder 38)
  - National Academy of Medicine, Venezuela, Corresponding Member, 1912 April 15; 54 (Folder 38)
  - Society of Physicians of Odessa, Honorary Member, 1912 October 1; 55 (Folder 39)
  - The Royal Society of Medicine and Natural Sciences, Brussels, Honorary Member, 1912 November 6; 56 (Folder 40)
  - The Royal Society of London, Honorary Foreign Member, 1912; 57 (Folder 40)
  - Society of Physicians, Archangel, Honorary Member, 1913 January 8; 58 (Folder 41)
  - Society of Natural Sciences, Braunschweig, Honorary Member, 1913 February 16; 59 (Folder 41)
  - Orlof Medical Society, Honorary Member, 1913 March 10; 60 (Folder 41)
  - Diploma indicating change of street name to Paul Ehrlich Strasse, copy of newspaper clip, 1910 December; 43a, b (Folder 30)
  - Society of Veterinary Medicine, Kazan, Honorary Member, 1913 March 31; 61 (Folder 41)
  - German Chemical Society, Berlin, Honorary Member (2 unsigned copies of diploma in addition: 62a and 62b), 1913 April 26; 62 (Folder 42)
  - Society of German Neurologists, Honorary Member, 1913 September 30; 63 (Folder 43)
  - Society of Biology, Paris, Honorary Member, 1913 December 27; 64 (Folder 43)
  - Medical-Surgical Society of Bologna, Corresponding Foreign Member, 1914 March 26; 65 (Folder 44)
  - Norwegian Scientific Society, Christiana, Foreign Member, 1914 March 27; 66 (Folder 45)
  - Cross of Meritul Sanitar, 1st class, Romania, 1914; 67 (Folder 46)
  - Order of the Rising Sun, Japan, undated; 68 (Folder 46)
  - Congress of Internal Medicine, undated; 69 (Folder 46)
  - Nobel diploma in case Leather-bound diploma engraved and painted by G. Hedberg, Swedish court engraver at the time of the award to Paul Ehrlich, 1908 October 29 (Package 7)
- Engagement time letters between Paul Ehrlich and Hedwig Pinkus
  Covering the period of February 1883 to August 1883. Paul and Hedwig married on Tuesday, August 14, 1883.
  There are 106 handwritten letters by Paul Ehrlich to Hedwig Pinkus and 103 by Hedwig to Paul. Two so-called "Brautbriefe" written by Paul on February 25 and 27, 1883 are of special interest. The February 25 letter was sent by Ehrlich's daughters in 1955 to Sir Henry Dale as a gift and memento. This letter was later sold and is therefore not part of this collection in the original; only a photo copy is available. There are 3 typescript copies of these 2 letters; none of the others have been transcribed.
  The letters are in chronological order but not integrated; Box No. 48 contains Hedwig's letters and Box No. 49 contains Paul's. There are some related letters by Hedwig's parents and wedding invitations in Box No. 48. Many of these letters have the original envelopes and stamps.
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 February 26 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 March 1, 3, 4, 5, 22, 23, 31 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 April 2, 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 18, 19, 20 (2), 21 (2), 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 29 (2) (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 May 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 (2), 6, 8, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 31 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 June 1, 2, 5 (2), 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12 (2), 14, 16 (2), 18, 19, 20, 22, 23 (2), 24, 26, 27, 28 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 July 8, 9, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 19, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 August 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Josef Pinkus to Ehrlich, 1883 February 23, 26 (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Josef Pinkus to Ehrlich, 1883 March 2, 4 (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Auguste Pinkus to Ehrlich, 1883 February 27 (Box 48, Folder 8)
    - 2 unaddressed wedding invitations with envelopes
    - 1 wedding invitation not addressed but in envelope addressed to Paul Ehrlich
    - 2 empty envelopes addressed to Paul Ehrlich
    - 1 postcard from a bookstore to Hedwig, 1881 January
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 February 25 (copy), 27 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 March 2, 4, 6, 24, 3, undated (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 April 1 (2), 3, 4, 5, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17 (2), 18 (2), 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26 (2), 29, 30 (2), 3 undated (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 May 1, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 20, 21, 26 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 June 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20 (2), 22 (2), 23 (2), 24, 25, 26 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Hedwig to Paul, 1883 July 8, 9 (2), 10, 11 (2), 12*, 13, 14 (2), 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 28 (2), 29, 30, 31 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Paul Ehrlich undated letters listed in April could be: April 6, 1883; April 7, 1883; April 14, 1883 12* small note in Frerichs' handwriting, announcing his absence from clinical rounds until Monday. Dated Berlin July 12, 1883, signed Prof. Frerichs, 1883 August 8 (2) (Box 49, Folder 7)
- Hedwig Ehrlich's Diary (Box 50)
  Handwritten diary by Hedwig Ehrlich starting November 6, (probably 1909), ending April 1911 and 2 photocopies with Hedwig's markings and notations.
- Reminiscences about Paul Ehrlich
  Essays by friends and colleagues of Paul Ehrlich sent to Hedwig after Paul's death
  Arrangement
  Alphabetical.
  - Dunham, Reminiscences about Ehrlich's visit to the U.S.A. in 1904, 2 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Ehrlich, Hedwig. Reminiscences and anecdotes, 43 handwritten pages, a handwritten booklet; typescript reminiscences 2 pages (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Hirsch, Karl. Essay on Ehrlich, typescript, 8 pages, same in Hedwig's handwriting. Essay on Ehrlich 2 typescript copies, 3 pages each, 3 pages each (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Knoche, Anna. Reminiscences. By Ehrlich's sister Anna, 2 items, 3 pages each (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - Meyer, Otto. Reminiscences about laboratory days, 7 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - Michaelis, Leonor. Essay on Ehrlich, 6 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - Neuman, Alfred. Essay on Ehrlich, 4 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 7)
  - Oppenheimer, Franz. Essay on Ehrlich, 2 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 8)
  - Pinkus, Felix. Essay on Ehrlich entitled: "Studieren geht uber probieren", 140 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 9)
  - Rosin, Herbert. Reminiscences by a school friend, 2 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 10)
  - Schmitz. Speech given at dedication of Ehrlich's birth-house, 7 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 11)
  - Schwerin, Hans. Essays and reminiscences by Ehrlich's grandson, 34 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 12)
    Handwritten note by Hedwig; copy of a letter by Hedwig, referring to the above material.
  - Tomarkin Foundation. Lecture held by unknown author in St. Moritz 1933: "25 years Salvarsan", sponsored by the Foundation (Box 51, Folder 13)
  - Venzmer, Gerhard. Essay on Ehrlich entitled: "Der die Zauberkugel fand", 120 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 14)
  - Waldeyer-Hartz. Essay on Ehrlich, 2 pages, typescript, 2 pages; Remin., typescript (Box 51, Folder 15)
  - Wilhelm. 1 sheet, 2 pages (Box 51, Folder 15)
  - Weigert, Abraham. Reminiscences about his own life, written in 1867, 9 pages, typescript copy (Box 51, Folder 16)
  - Weinberg, Barbara. Translation of a chapter from the book "Nine Jews", by Bolitho, 27 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 17)
  - Unknown author # 1. Essay on Ehrlich, 39 pages, typescript, 39 pages (2 copies) and many (about 100) handwritten notes (Box 51, Folder 18)
  - Unknown author # 2. Essay on Ehrlich, 17 pages, typescript, 17 pages with man corrections (Box 51, Folder 19)
  - Unknown author # 3. Essay on Ehrlich, handwritten, 5 pages (Box 51, Folder 20)
  - Unknown author # 4. Essay on Ehrlich, most likely by Felix Pinkus, with comment by Martha Marquardt, 7 pages, typescript (Box 51, Folder 21)
- Hedwig Ehrlich's correspondence, after Paul Ehrlich's death
  (most of these seem to be reminiscences which may have been solicited by Hedwig).
  - Berliner, Arnold, 1918 August 22; 1 letter (Box 51, Folder 22)
  - Cohn, Eugen, 1919 March 22; 1 letter (Box 51, Folder 22)
  - Heyman, Bruno, 1926 December 19 1927 February 8; 2 reprints with dedication (Box 51, Folder 22)
  - Hoffman, 1918 September 23; 1 letter (Box 51, Folder 22)
  - Kaiser Wilhelm Gesellschaft, 1915 September 28; 1 letter (Box 51, Folder 22)
    Acknowledgment of returned order which Ehrlich received after his death.
  - Knoche, Gert, Ehrlich genealogy, 1938 August 8; 1 item (Box 51, Folder 22)
  - Marquardt, Martha, 1948 August 25; 1 letter (Box 51, Folder 22)
  - Meyer, Otto, 1918 (Box 51, Folder 22)
    Typescript copy of this letter is in Reminiscence File Folder #6.